<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The paragon of Persia; or The lavvyers looking-glasse Opened in a sermon at S. Maries in Oxford, at the Assises, the 7 day of Iuly, 1624. By William Hayes, Master of Arts of Magdalen Hall.</title>
            <author>Hayes, William, b. 1595 or 6.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02835</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12973</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116667</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851883</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851883</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17176</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02835)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17176)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 990:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The paragon of Persia; or The lavvyers looking-glasse Opened in a sermon at S. Maries in Oxford, at the Assises, the 7 day of Iuly, 1624. By William Hayes, Master of Arts of Magdalen Hall.</title>
                  <author>Hayes, William, b. 1595 or 6.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Lichfield, and Iames Short,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: The lawyers looking-glasse.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17176:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PARAGON OF PERSIA; <hi>OR</hi> THE LAVVYERS <hi>LOOKING-GLASSE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Opened in a Sermon at S. MARIES in Oxford, at the Aſſiſes, the 7 day of Iuly, 1624.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> WILLIAM HAYES, <hi>Maſter of Arts of</hi> Magdalen Hall.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Terent. Adolph. Act 3. Scen. 4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <l>Inſpicere, tanquam in <hi>ſpeculum,</hi> in vitas omnium</l>
               <l>Iubeo, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ex alijs ſumere exemplum tibi.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Make others practice as a <hi>Glaſſe,</hi> to ſhew,</l>
               <l>What thou muſt doe, &amp; what thou muſt eſchew.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>AT OXFORD,</hi> Printed by <hi>Iohn Lichfield,</hi> and <hi>Iames Short.</hi> Anno Dom. 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17176:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17176:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL Sir RICHARD GIFFORD Knight, the much honoured Patron of my ſtudies, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the <hi>religious Lady his wife,</hi> all grace and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right worſhipfull,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His was once the Preface to <hi>Dauids</hi> thankeſ-giuing, <hi>What ſhall I render?</hi> &amp; in a borrowed ſenſe it may be mine <hi>Quid retribuam?</hi> Could I i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate his reſolution, <hi>I ſhould not giue that which coſt me nothing,</hi> 2 Sam. 24 (for ſo I value my beſt endeauours, when they are counter-poyſed with your merits.) I know my dependance &amp; engagements, &amp; find my ſelfe guilty of too weake performance: yet ſuch as I haue, my piety makes it Gods, and my duty, yours. And I wiſh the worth of this, which I preſent vnto your hands, could as eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſatisfie your deſerts, as the ſight of it wil ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mens requeſts. Then might the ſame fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, which hath ſuſtained the Author, haue
<pb facs="tcp:17176:3"/> greater encouragement to protect the works: Then might I hazard it among theſe ſeuere eyes, which daylie ſcanne our ſhops and ſtaules: whereas now the number of my Copies ſhall not exceed the number of my friends. Yet in this fewneſſe, I congratulate my owne prouidence, that I leaue my ſelfe libertie to chooſe my rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; which (as nigh as I can) ſhall be onely ſuch, as either will reſpect this Taske for my ſake, or me for my owne, or both it and me for yours. The very name in my Dedication, doth promiſe me to be speake ſome in <hi>Dauids</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate language for <hi>Abſalom, Deale gently for my ſake with the yong man.</hi> If ſo, let their loue enioy the vſe, &amp; not grudge your deſerts, the patronage. Thus while you encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage me with your <hi>Countenance,</hi> &amp; they with their acceptance, I ſhal praiſe God for his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, &amp; ſolace my ſelfe in your fauours. So re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in hope of this happineſſe, I attend you with my prayers, which ſhall be inceſſant both for you and yours from</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips in all duty and ſeruice vnfainedly deuoted WILLIAM HAYES.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Oxford
<date>
                     <hi>this 20 of Iuly, 1624.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:17176:3"/>
            <head>
               <bibl>ESTER 1.15. Part of the verſe.</bibl> What ſhall we doe vnto the Queene <hi>Vaſthi</hi> according to Law? &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Text may perſwade you, I am making towards <hi>Perſia,</hi> to ſee the King ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queting with his Peeres. A ſight as well worth your notice as my paines. Let your thoughts but accompany me, I will vndertake to ſhew you <hi>Ahaſuerus,</hi> whom <note n="a" place="margin">Ioſeph. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiq. Iudaic. lib. <hi>11.</hi> cap. <hi>4 1.</hi> Eſd. c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ioſephus</hi> and others call <hi>Darius Hyſtaſpis,</hi> ſitting in his royall palace; where (that <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicus apparatus</hi>) his ſtately complements in entertaining his ſubiects, prooued him not more a <hi>Prince</hi> then a <hi>Perſian.</hi> Such was wont to be the port of that nation, that they would ſurpaſſe other Countries as well in magnificence as dominion. Inſomuch that one <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. In hiſt. à Photi<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> excerptis.</note> 
               <hi>Cteſias</hi> and <hi>Dion</hi> deliuer in their hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; that the King had at meales 15 thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17176:4"/> a day in his Palace. Now to make vp the ſolemnity of thoſe meetings, <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> invites the Queene his wife, that her comely preſence might adde glory to his Feſtiuals. But we finde in the Text, <hi>ſhee refuſed to come at the Kings command. Serarius</hi> the Ieſuite (an enimy to Kings prerogatiues by his profeſſion) hath the face to approue her diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyall action; and taxeth our <hi>Brentius</hi> for diſliking her palpable diſobedience. But hee whoſe ſoueraignty might haue made his word a law proceeds againſt her, not after his priuate humour, but according to law. To which purpoſe hee appeales to his Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges (fit oracles for a King in execution of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice) and referres himſelfe to their adviſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What ſhall we doe vnto the Queene</hi> Vaſthi <hi>according to law?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein is ſet before vs,
<list>
                  <item>1 An offender to be adiudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; <hi>The Queene Vaſthi.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 Deliberation before iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; <hi>What ſhall we doe?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 The level and rule of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; <hi>The Law.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>What ſhall wee doe vnto the Queene Vaſthi according to law?</hi> Beginne (I pray)</item>
               </list> with the party to be ſentenced, the Queene
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17176:4"/> 
               <hi>Vaſthi. Quaeres</hi> about this woman could make me out-runne your attention as far as ſome in this point doe their reaſon. But I o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſcruples concerning her perſon, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent my ſelfe with the evidence of her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. The Text is manifeſt ſhee was the Queene.</p>
            <p>Could any thing priuiledge diſloyalty toward Kings, eminence and alliance might be faire pretences: but neither of theſe could yeeld her adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage. The reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is preſt by one of the Iudges in the 3 next enſuing verſes. In effect it is this. The offence of the Queen an eminent perſon, would become exemplary, therefore muſt be cenſured with the greater ſeuerity. Such is the ſeruile baſeneſſe of our diſpoſition, that ſinne it ſelfe ſhall not want imitation. Nay <note n="c" place="margin">Auguſt. de pec. meritis. cap. <hi>1.2.3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Auſtin</hi> tels vs, it was once the opinion of the <hi>Pelagians,</hi> That on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imitation is the cauſe of original ſin. That Father did not, and I dare not, yeeld to them for originall; but I may ſafely for actuall: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially for thoſe offences, which gaine countenance by a great ones practice. Nay, 'tis ſometimes in faſhion, to take the reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance and patterne of a naturall imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. <note n="d" place="margin">Tull. de o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratore lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Imitari etiam vitia voluit:</hi> Let <hi>Caius Fimbria</hi> but ſpeake clowniſh, 'tis hard but
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17176:5"/> ſome <hi>Fuſius</hi> will take vp his language. <note n="e" place="margin">Plutarch. moral.</note> 
               <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotles</hi> authority, and <hi>Plato's</hi> eſtimation, can make ſects of crump-backes and ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mering tongues. 'Tis the vnhappy priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of greatneſſe, to warrant both their own and Natures errours. Hence it is, that ſo many vnaduiſed idiots borrow their juſt ruines, taking vp crimes on truſt, that they may periſh vpon credit: for ſuch are not ſwayed by reaſon ſo much, as by opinion. Let an admired Phariſee but ſay, CHRIST ought to dye; the vulgar dare blaſpheme themſelues to hell for his company, <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 7.51.</note> 
               <hi>As your fathers did</hi> (ſaid <hi>Steuen</hi> in the Acts) <hi>ſo doe yee:</hi> you ſinne by preſcription, and haue authority for your damnation, <hi>Habet ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid ex iniquo omne magnum exemplum, &amp;c.</hi> As <hi>Caſſius</hi> hath it in <hi>Tacitus.</hi> The example of great ones, doth wrong to all ſorts. It teacheth the good to be euill, and the euill to be worſe: for the luſtre of their eminence adornes the deformity of their offences; and cheates the world with the faire garb of their perſons; eſpecially being beheld by ſuch partiall eyes, as cannot diſcerne the truth of things from their appearance. When a peſant meetes luxurie in <hi>Socrates</hi> gowne, he dares to be ſuch, hauing ſo faire a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17176:5"/> cloake for his ſin. Aske but <note n="g" place="margin">Tert. Apol.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> or <note n="h" place="margin">Aug. lib. <hi>2.</hi> de ciuit Dei. cap <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auſtin,</hi> their cenſure on the gods of the Heathen; they'l tell you that no men were more inceſtuous, then they that were taught by their <hi>Iupiters</hi> practice. <note n="i" place="margin">Ter. E<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> And that wretch in the Comedian, would take leaue to ſinne vnder his protection. What? <hi>Iupiter</hi> memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable for fornication, and I ſo chaſte, being but a ſilly man? <hi>Ego homuncio non face<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem?</hi> Thus euery ſlip is a crime in a Leader, ſince it doth become a rule of errour. If a meane one offend, his ſinne is neglected as much as his perſon: but the ſuppoſed wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, grauity, and juſtice of ſuperiours, win credit to their vileſt actions. Well then might judge <hi>Mines</hi> in <note n="k" place="margin">Lucian. dial. mort.</note> 
               <hi>Lucian,</hi> acquit <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratus</hi> on this condition, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, See thou teach not thy offence vnto others. <note n="l" place="margin">Cyp. epiſt. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus enim non tantum geritur, ſed &amp; docetur,</hi> ſaith <hi>Cypr.</hi> for ſuch as theſe doe not ſo much act, as teach offences. Therefore 'tis preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that the torments of ſuch encreaſe in hel, as the liuing increaſe in ſin through their example. No maruaile then that they are ſo afflicted in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Iohns</hi> viſion; <hi>Who are</hi> ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward there, as <hi>the Kings of the earth,</hi> &amp; <hi>the great men, and the chiefe captaines; and the mighty men, to hide themſelues in the deus,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17176:6"/> and in the rockes of the mountaines?</hi> Rev. 6.15. They that once made the earth tremble with their power, doe now tremble like the earth vnder the hand of the God of power. They that once did teach to offend by their examples, are now taught what it is to be precedents of offences. If God deale thus on his heauenly Tribunal, no reaſon his Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties on earth ſhould be partiall. If he ſpare them leaſt, whoſe offences are exemplary, then <hi>what ſhall be done vnto the Queen Vast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi?</hi> Againe, it is the cuſtome of greatneſſe, to challenge impunitie, by reaſon of their emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence; ſo that in time they'l out-face autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; then in this reſpect <hi>what ſhall be done vnto the Queene Vaſthi?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſtamp of ſoueraignty is ſacred; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore quickly defaced by a rebellious hand. <hi>Touch not mine anointed,</hi> preuailes nothing with a ſeditious mind; eſpecially where the hand is as well armed with power, as the heart with diſobedience. None but ſuch as are able to make head, dare demand, <hi>Who is Dauid?</hi> 'Tis conceit of equality that encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rageth great ones, to a conteſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates. They dare imitate <hi>Socrates,</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">Tul. <hi>1.</hi> de orat.</note> 
               <hi>Qui Dominus videbatur eſſe Iudicum,</hi> whoſe proud innocence diſdain'd the Iudges, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17176:6"/> made his vnmannerly zeale, laugh Iuſtice in the face. Should one aske herein the <hi>Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> aduiſe, they would preſcribe an <hi>Oſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſme,</hi> baniſhment at leaſt for ſuch daring offenders. As <hi>Cato</hi> perſwaded the <hi>Senate</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> that <hi>Carthage</hi> was an enemy too powerfull to be ſo nigh them. Then the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of the State muſt be purchaſ'd with the ruine of <hi>Carthage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lawes had neuer reſembled cob-webs, had there not bin ſuch ſtrong offenders. The feeble gnats yeeld to the leaſt reſiſtance, whereas violent fowles will not be reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by ſuch contemptible engins. 'Tis eaſie to vanquiſh an vnarmed ſlaue, and to inſult on the weaknes of a manicled captiue: but to ſubdue thoſe that like him in the Goſpel, <hi>neither feare God, nor care for men,</hi> requires both power and reſolution. Or howſoeuer theſe high tranſgreſſours may eſcape mans judgment, or <note n="n" place="margin">1 Cor. 4.3</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Mans</hi> day, (as <hi>Paul</hi> calls it) yet the Lord of hoſts hath a day, if they'l beleeue <hi>Eſay, which ſhall be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon euery one that is proud and loftie, and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon euery one that is lifted vp, and he ſhall bee brought lowe, And vpon all the Cedars of Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banon, that are high, &amp; lifted vp, and vpon all the oakes of Baſhan.</hi> 2 of <hi>Eſay.</hi> They ſhall
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17176:7"/> then confeſſe with vanquiſht <hi>Iulian,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Thou haſt ouercome, O Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaean. This out-brauing wretch (as <note n="o" place="margin">Theod. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clef. hiſt. lib. <hi>3</hi> cap. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> tis in <hi>Theodorit</hi>) that but now did ſwell with vaunting threats, lay groueling on the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welcome ground, when he apprehended the terrours of God. Such acts of diuine Iuſtice, preſcribe courage to temporall magiſtrats, and bid them not feare the moſt puiſſant of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders. This alſo we learne of humane poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: Then <hi>what ſhall be done vnto the Queene Vasthi?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to make way for reſolution, may it pleaſe you to examine, how her condition doth agree to this our occaſion. Our Land doth afford many <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſthi's,</hi> eminent offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; the authority of whoſe perſons, drawes others to ſecond them in their crimes. It is peſterd alſo with powerfull offenders, whoſe daring greatnes doth promiſe them immunity from puniſhments. But the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull juſtice of our gracious Soueraigne, doth with <hi>Ahaſuerus,</hi> depend on his Aſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, for the cenſuring of theſe enormities. I could carry back your memories but a few ſcores of yeares, and there ſhew you a King of this land, relying on the Iudges determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, <hi>What ſhould be done vnto the Queene?</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:17176:7"/> There are more which admire his impartia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, then approue his fact. But our preſent happineſſe, bids me confine my ſpeech to our own times, and apply to your conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces a noble preſident for your happy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings. That ſincere Court, whereof your Honors were lately members, durſt adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture on the States moſt potent enemies. They had, I preſume, both your approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and aſſiſtance. Wherfore, ride on, ye men of renowne, and proſper; good lucke haue you with your honor. You may in your <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit</hi> meet with ſuch, whoſe power doth arme their crimes, and makes them ſinne au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in the face. Therefore let me beſpeak you, as the Prophet did that God whoſe diſpenſation doth tearme you Gods: you aske, <hi>What ſhall we doe?</hi> I anſwere in his words, <note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 83.</note> 
               <hi>Doe vnto them as was done to the Midianites, vnto Siſera, and vnto Iabin at the brooke of Kiſon, which periſhed at Endor, and became as the dung of the earth.</hi> Let an impartiall doome purſue their tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and let their due ſhame attend them to their graues. <note n="q" place="margin">Non tam ut ipſi pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, quàm ut alios pereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do deterre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant. Senec.</note> 
               <hi>Seneca</hi> ſhall giue you the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: Not ſo much that they may periſh, but to terrifie others by their periſhing.<note n="r" place="margin">2 Sam. 24 17.</note> 
               <hi>I haue ſinned</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid) I haue done wickedly,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17176:8"/> but theſe ſheepe, what haue they done?</hi> His conſcience thought the puniſhment prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous, that his people ſhould be led as ſheep to the ſlaughter, and yet he eſcape his deſerued cenſure. And among vs how many ſilly ſheep ſacrifice their cheape liues to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe the law for their offences? whereas e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent tranſgreſſours, that ſin with an high hand, make ſhift to flye aboue the reach of Iuſtice. I feare, ſometimes they borrow wings of that Doue in the Pſalmes, <hi>which is couered with ſiluer wings, and her feathers of gold,</hi> Pſal. 68. 'Tis they that ſin, they that doe wickedly, and in compariſon of them, theſe ſheep, what haue they done? The pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of theſe impotent wretches, doth not argue the Iudges valour, but the lawes iuſtice. The edge of authority wil be thought but dull and growne ruſty, except it wound others, beſide them that cannot make reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. 'Tis mercie to let thoſe no longer liue, in whom impriſonment hath left ſcarce life enough to dye. So that did we not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue in them ſpeech, whereby the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher diſtinguiſht men from beaſts, wee ſhould ſcarce diſtinguiſh theſe from carca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. There they ſtand arraigned, not more the priſoners of the King, then of death.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17176:8"/> Some of them haue liued long enough to ſee their laſting calamities out-liue their friends and fortunes: inſomuch, that their aged eies can doe them no other ſeruice, but ſee them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues miſerable, and weep for their diſtreſſe. That our Lawes doe vanquiſh theſe halfe-dead vaſſals, proues them (I confeſſe) im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiall, yet nothing powerfull. <note n="ſ" place="margin">Conſent of time.</note> 
               <hi>Cambyſes</hi> would ſhew, what his tyrannie could in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, and what his hand durſt execute, by ſhooting a great mans Sonne to the heart. Then doth appeare the force of our Lawes, and the courage of our Magiſtrates, when <hi>Phoneas</hi>-like, they thruſt the ſword of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice through the nobleſt tranſgreſſours: He was only to ſacrifice for the ſin of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; yet he durſt ſacrifice <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Coſbi.</hi> Num. 25.</note> two Princes of the people for their daring ſinne. A fact that deſerued not more thankes from the Iewes for its benefit, then it doth from vs for its example.</p>
            <p>But by perſwading impartiality to great, ones, I intend not to procure impunity for inferiours; No,<note n="n" place="margin">Quiſque exercetur paenis, vete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumque ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum Supplicia ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendat— Aen. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> excercetur paenis, &amp;c.</hi> Wee haue a good rule from <hi>Ezekiels</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, <hi>The ſame ſoule that ſinneth, ſhall dye,</hi> Ezek. 18. If the ſame, then the meane as well as the mighty: for though they are not ſo
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17176:9"/> hurtfull, yet they are as guilty. And yet they are hurtful enough too: for what they want in power, they make vp in nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber. A <note n="x" place="margin">Varro au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor eſt, à cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niculis ſuffoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum in Hiſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niâ oppidum &amp;c Hiſt lib. <hi>8.</hi> cap. <hi>29.</hi> pli.</note> Town in <hi>Spaine</hi> may as well be vndermined with Conies, and another in <hi>Theſſalie</hi> by Moles, as by the ſtrongeſt pioners. Vnited force in contemptible complices, may be anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to more powerfull machinations. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let Iuſtice haue her due courſe on both ſides: and let the Embleme make her hood-winkt, but not blind. Let her ſee offences on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and puniſh them; but not offenders, leſt her con<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ivence ſpare them. She had (I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe) well tutor'd the <note n="y" place="margin">T. Liu. dec. <hi>1.</hi> lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> Conſul <hi>Brutus,</hi> when ſhe taught him to play the executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and put off a father. So that when pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment was inflicted on his children, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his eyes, he rould ſee the <hi>malefactors,</hi> but not his ſonnes.<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ariſt. Rhetor. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> And paſſionleſſe <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi> could endure the Lictors to ſhedde his childes blood, without ſhedding of his own teares. Then is <hi>Iuſtice</hi> her ſelfe, when ſhe can ouer-looke Nature, and all reſpects whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer. Then will ſhe take heed leſt ſhe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place her mercie, and ſo make it degenerate into crueltie; for though there be no mercy in cruelty, yet there is a crueltie in ſome kind of mercy. <hi>Eſt quaedam crudelis miſericordia,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:17176:9"/> ſaith the prouerbe, <hi>and the mercies of the wicked are cruell,</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Prouerb. 12.10.</note> ſaith the Holy Ghoſt. Now if <hi>Iuſtice</hi> ſpare great ones for their might, and meane ones for their miſery, <hi>Haec eſt crudelis miſericordia,</hi> this is a cruell mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. Cruell to the State, in cauſing Lawes, (which <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> cals, the <hi>ſoule of a ſtate</hi>) to be but dead letters. Cruell again to the Lawes, in making them ſtales for mens ſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter purpoſes. Then let the ſword be bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſht on all ſides, and ſtrike alike all rankes and conditions. And though charity to the State, allowes me not to intreat for their liues; yet <hi>Dauids</hi> charity to their perſons, bids me petition for their ſoules; Lord, <hi>let the ſorrowfull ſighing of the priſoners come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee, according to the greatneſſe of thy power preſerue thou thoſe that are appointed to dye,</hi> Pſal. 79. And ſo from the perſon to be adjudged, I paſſe to deliberation before Iudgement, <hi>What ſhall we doe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In doubtfull actions, <hi>Aquinas 1<hi rend="sup">a</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">ae</hi>,</hi> makes deliberation the firſt act of our rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and will haue Iudgment come between that and election. So noble is the ſoules naturall progreſſe, that ſhe reſolues on no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, <hi>hand ouer head,</hi> but vpon mature ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe. And 'tis well that a King, <hi>a god on
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17176:10"/> earth,</hi> can remember, he hath ſo much of man about him, as that he needeth this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation: for he that contemneth all aduiſe, is below a beaſt, he that wanteth none, is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue a man. It were to be wiſht, that all good Princes might enioy <hi>Sauls</hi> preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue to ouer-top the people <hi>by the head</hi> as well as <hi>out-reach them</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Longae Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum manus. Adag.</note> 
               <hi>with the hand:</hi> or all might with <hi>Salomon,</hi> haue hearts as large as their dominions. But they muſt content themſelues with that abridgement in <hi>Euri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pides,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Eurip.</note> 
               <hi>One man cannot ſee all;</hi> and with that other in <hi>Tacitus,</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Nec unius mens tantae molis eſt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pax. Tacit.</note> 
               <hi>One man cannot beare all;</hi> Anſwerable to that of <hi>Iethro</hi> vnto <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, This thing is too heauy for thee, thou art not able to performe it thy ſelfe alone,</hi> Exod. 18. The head might quickly draw the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to inconveniences, wer't not for intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence from the eyes and eares. Therefore the King, the head of Iſrael ſometimes, muſt enquire <hi>where the Seer dwels:</hi> And who is fitter to be the <hi>Seer of Iſrael,</hi> then <hi>Samuel</hi> that iudgeth Iſrael? His diſcerning thoughts muſt both ſee the peoples duties, &amp; fore-ſee the Princes dangers: Wherfore both Prince and people repaire to him as to an Oracle; with <hi>(Quid agendum) What ſhall we doe?</hi> Happy <hi>State</hi> of ours, where the <hi>coactiue</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:17176:10"/> power, thus ſubmits it ſelfe to the guidance of the <hi>directiue!</hi> &amp; thrice happy Soueraigne which can heare his power flatter him, that he may doe what he will, yet ſo yeelds to convenience, that he will not doe what he may. Hence it is that he ſcarce attempts any thing, but as 'twere with this Motto, <hi>Quid agendum? What ſhall we doe?</hi> Men in their <hi>Panegyrickes</hi> may ſtyle him a <hi>Salomon,</hi> a mirrour of wiſedome: of late eſpecially he hath made it good; and neuer gained a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter opinion of wiſedome, then when he leaſt relyed vpon his wiſedome. In high matters of deepeſt conſequence, it is his vſuall Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament-phraſe, <hi>I craue your aduiſe.</hi> Such was the milde method of glorious <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> when he allayed the iarres of diſturbed Chriſtendome, <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Socrat. eccleſ hiſt. l. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> He cryed not out, <hi>This I will haue done,</hi> but meekely entertain'd the whole Councels reſolution. Bleſſed time when a mans tongue may bee as free as his opinion; and when he may with <hi>Tacitus,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Rarâ tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porum faelici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, ubi ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire quae veli<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; quae ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tias dicere licet. Tacit. procem. hiſt.</note> not only think what he wil, but alſo ſpeak what he thinks. Let the like happines of ours be a ioyfull memoriall for enſuing ages and let vn-borne poſteritie haue cauſe to triumph in the matter of our glorie.</p>
            <p>But I leaue this conſultation in buſineſſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17176:11"/> of <hi>State,</hi> and paſſe to deliberation before iudgment, <hi>Quid agendum? What ſhall wee doe?</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ariſt. <hi>3.</hi> Eth.</note> Things of ſmall importance, may for a while poſſeſſe our fancies, but ſeldome take vp our ſerious thoughts. We ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſolue, <hi>This we will doe,</hi> whereas weighty affaires deſerue pawſes and demurs; <hi>What ſhall we doe?</hi> You are now (beloued) in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haſuecus</hi> caſe, expecting when the Iudges will paſſe their ſentence: The one vpon mens eſtates, the other vpon their perſons. The leaſt is a matter of no ordinary conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence; I need not exhort either <hi>Iudge</hi> or <hi>Iurer,</hi> otherwiſe then God inioyned in the like caſe, <hi>Thou ſhalt enquire and ſearch, and aske diligently;</hi> in the 13 of Deuteronomy. Queſtionleſſe he well weighed the value of a man, and priz'd his life at an higher rate, then to haue raſh decrees make hauocke of his blood. <note n="h" place="margin">—meruit quo crimine ſervus Supplicium? quis teſtis adeſt? quis detulit? Iuv. Sat. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> Such a cauſe deſerues an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt enquirie, concerning the matter of the obiection, the reputation of the witneſſes &amp; the diſpoſition of the accuſers. <note n="i" place="margin">Targ. Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nath. in <hi>Num. 9.8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Rabbi Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathan</hi> obſerues of <hi>Moſes,</hi> that being to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine ordinary inditements, he did haſten; but in the cauſe of thoſe that were to dye, his ſentence was not ſo ſpeedy. <hi>In Targ.</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Nulla un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam de morte homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis cunctatio longa eſt. Juven. ibid.</note> No delayes can be tedious, no paines ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17176:11"/> no interrogatories frivolous, when a mans life depends on the <hi>Iudges</hi> and <hi>Iurers</hi> diligence. His life, which Satan perceiued to be ſo much worth, that a man will ranſome it <note n="l" place="margin">Iob 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>with all he hath.</hi> Precious gale of breath, that coſt the mother ſo many pangs and throes to bring it forth! that coſt its owner ſo much care to preſerue it! ſo much ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes to cheriſh it! and muſt hee now at laſt, through the malice of accuſers, or the periury of witneſſes, be depriued of it, which for want of deliberation are not diſcouered? <note n="m" place="margin">Vlpian.</note> How doth old Rome, that allowed nine houres for defence of each petty cauſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne our ouerture, and our haſtie procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings? ſhall they haue ſuch large reſpite for their eſtates, and we ſo litle for our liues? Well may the life of man be termed a buble if it deſerue but ſuch a momentary triall. But obſerue the Holy Ghoſt, Deut 19. <hi>The Iudges ſhall make diligent inquiſition;</hi> which implieth long aduiſe, and mature delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But while I exhort to deliberation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore iudgment, a tedious ſute long depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, prevents my exhortation. The forlorne <hi>Client</hi> is tired out with delayes, while his Advocat demurs about his cauſe, as long as <note n="n" place="margin">Deliberan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di unum ſibi diem poſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lauit, &amp;c. Cicer. de nat. Deorum.</note>
               <hi>Simonides</hi> did about the nature of GOD.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17176:12"/> 
               <hi>Hieron</hi> muſt firſt allow him a day, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards two; at laſt the longer he was about it, the leſſe he had determin'd. Thus while they are conſulting and doubting what may be done, the deluded Client is quite vnd one. <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Charron</hi> of wiſedome.</note> Therefore a certaine Lawyer doth aduiſe euery King to aboliſh that <hi>pernicious myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of pleading:</hi> you ſee, he makes bold with his own profeſſion; but I forbeare ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptory and tart language; and reprehend it no otherwiſe then milde <hi>Iſmenias</hi> did his Schollars, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <note n="p" place="margin">Plut. in vit. Demet.</note> 
               <hi>It ought not thus to be.</hi> No, it ought not to be, that the Lawyers <hi>(What ſhall we doe?)</hi> in a pretended delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſhould driue the <hi>Client</hi> to his <hi>(Quid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gam?)</hi> in an exigent of paſſion, and ſo make him crye with thoſe in the Acts, which were pricked at the heart with ſorrow and anxie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>Men and brethren, what ſhall I doe?</hi> I am now a companion for that diſtreſſed Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, <note n="q" place="margin">Luk. 16.3</note> 
               <hi>Digge I cannot, and to begge I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed.</hi> Thoſe many acres which I once poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt, are through lingring ſutes brought to ſix or ſeuen foot to hide my carkeiſe. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can I enioy that, without the ſubmiſſe Epitaph of <hi>Cyrus;</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">O homo, ne mihi ſepultu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram invide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as. <hi>Conſ. of time.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>O man, envie not vnto me this ſmall parcell wherin to bury me.</hi> Thus hauing nothing left of what he was, but the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17176:12"/> remembrance, he paſſeth from a tedious iudgment on earth, to one in heauen more ſpeedy, ſuch as <hi>Paul</hi> tels vs, <hi>ſhall be in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in the twinkling of an eye;</hi> and he that wanted the fauour to be iudged heere, may haue the honour to bee a Iudge heereafter. <hi>Know yee not that the Saints ſhall iudge the world?</hi> 1 Cor. 6.2. Their nimble thoughts ſhall not be clogg'd with needleſſe demurs, but will inſtantly approue what the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Iudge decrees. And Lord, let this chearful expedition haſten the zeale of our earthly Iudges, that thy people may haue quick diſpatch from miſery, and thy truth an increaſe of its due glory. And leſt thy Vice-gerents ſhould through miſpriſion or connivence be miſ-led; giue them vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to know the law, and grace to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it as their vn-erring guide, which is my laſt part, The leuell and rule of iudgment <hi>The Law. What ſhall we doe vnto the Queen Vaſthi according to Law?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The poſitiue Law, and Man, were once of an equall extention; <hi>One Law, and one Man.</hi> That Law accidentally taught him to know Sin; the increaſe of Sin hath taught his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity to know good Lawes. <hi>Ex malis mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus bonae lages.</hi> When the Lawes of nature
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17176:13"/> would not ſerue the turne, humane power, put on Maieſtie, and angry Iuſtice learn'd how to diſcipline their enormities with a rougher hand. So that at laſt, varietie of Lawes beganne almoſt to preuent their crimes; <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> makes them <note n="ſ" place="margin">Inſtit. lib. <hi>1</hi> Tit. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nationall</hi> &amp; <hi>Ciuill.</hi> Thoſe, naturall reaſon made common to euery Country, theſe vpon particular oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, were peculiar to ſuch a ſociety. <note n="t" place="margin">Aquin. <hi>1<hi rend="sup">a</hi> 2</hi>ae. quaeſt. <hi>94.</hi> art <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> Therefore 'tis the rule of <hi>Aquinas,</hi> that a Law muſt agree with time &amp; place, 1<hi rend="sup">a</hi> 2ae, q. 95. art. 3. It ſeemes there was ſome Law proper to the Perſians, that took hold of the Queenes diſobedience. And it was a good precedent of the King, being aboue that Law, to ſubmit himſelfe to the direction of the Law. <hi>What ſhall we doe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Law?</hi> Hereby a <hi>King</hi> is diſtinguiſht from a <hi>Tyrant.</hi> The King doth meaſure his attempts by Iuſtice; the other, Iuſtice by his power. The Tyrants force is his equity, and the ſword his duty. Laborious cruelty is but ſport to his guilty hands, till his wild &amp; vnbridled paſſions haue run out of breath in a curreer of blood. The pleaſure of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modus</hi> was Law enough to warrant the mangling and maſſacres of his ſubiects, by making them enter the liſt with beaſts. O
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17176:13"/> that exceſſe of power ſhould ſo tranſport one beyond nature, as that his will ſhould be all his reaſon, to rank men with creatures ſo vnreaſonable! wherefore one in <hi>Seneca</hi> would haue thoſe to be leaſt free, which haue power to be moſt guilty: and wiſheth it not lawfull for ſuch to haue liberty to doe that which is vnlawfull to be done.</p>
            <p>But what? Shal any dare to limit ſoueraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and preſcribe Maieſtie its duty? ſhall he that enioyes the ſubiection of others by the law, be ſubiect himſelfe to the law? No, in no other ſenſe then that of <hi>Aquinas. Quantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad vim directivam non coactivam,</hi> in 1<hi rend="sup">a</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">ae</hi> of his Summes. Not that the lawe ſhould drawe him by compulſion, but lead him by directiue perſwaſion. <note n="v" place="margin">In Decret. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Tit. <hi>2.</hi> Cap. Cum omnes.</note> If hee conforme his actions to the preſcript of the lawes, it is of his owne accord, if he doe not, is he liable to acount? Yes, but it is only to God. Againſt thee only haue I ſinned, ſaith King <hi>Dauid.</hi> Pſalm. 51. Thoſe modeſt times had not the face to capitulate with their Soueraignes. The pride of faction had not yet hatcht this rebellious doctrine, <hi>That if Kings obey not laws, ſubiects haue leaue to diſobey their kings</hi> No; let it glory in no ancienter author then <hi>New Rome;</hi> and in no better ſucceſſe then
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17176:14"/> confuſion. And ſeeing it owes it ſelfe to Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuited Patrons, let it be baniſht this land to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with their perſons. And let them whom it concernes be inquiſitiue for auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riz'd <hi>Rauiliakes,</hi> ſuch as doe not value the price of a man, much leſſe of a Prince: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a fee ſhould neuer perſwade them to hazard their owne liues; nor to rifle for a few peeces of coyne in the bowels of their Soueraigne, and ſo ſell his deere blood for an houres wages.</p>
            <p>But while I exempt Princes from humane cenſures, I incourage not their neglect of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane lawes. The law is the life of a ſtate, &amp; their practice is the life of the law. Then it concernes them that haue moſt power to ui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olate lawes to haue moſt care to fulfill the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <note n="x" place="margin">Non tam imperio no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis opus qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exemplo. Plin. Pan.</note> Elſe the imitating vulgar will grow vnru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the example of their Rulers. Which his Maieſty implies in aduiſe to his ſonne in 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> booke of his <hi>Baſilicon Doron.</hi> Wherefore himſelfe, meaſures not the law by his owne will, but conformes his will to the meaſure of the law. This is his practice; &amp; this is the duty of all Iudges: <hi>What ſhall wee doe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to law?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which words admit of a double ſenſe. Firſt, <hi>According to law;</hi> that is, as much as
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17176:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> the law inioynes. Secondly, <hi>According to law;</hi> that is, No more then the law intends. And firſt of the firſt ſenſe; as much as the law inioynes; <hi>What ſhall we doe according to Law?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Iuſtinian. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Tit. <hi>2.</hi> inſtitut.</note>That Imperiall giuer of the law, makes giuing euery one his owne the end of the law. And I deſire no iuſter diſtribution then S. <hi>Paules,</hi> in 13 to the Rom. <hi>The Magiſtrate is the miniſter of God, to thee that doſt well, for good, but if thou that which is evill, bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid.</hi> The law then doth aſſigne to euery publique action, <hi>Reward, or Puniſhment,</hi> as its due guerdon. The leaſt open good may challenge ſome reward; if thou gain nothing elſe, yet the Apoſtle promiſeth, <hi>Thou ſhalt haue praiſe:</hi> But if thou doe not well, ſinne lyeth at the dore; God made it the doom of <hi>Cain,</hi> and the law makes it thine. <hi>Sinne lyeth,</hi> that is, puniſhment, the reward of ſinne; by an Hebrew <hi>metalepſis,</hi> as I am warranted by <note n="a" place="margin">Parae. &amp;c. in locum.</note> approued authors. Now this puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment without the <hi>Law</hi> were but a wooden ſword in the hand of a grim Anticke, able to awe none beſide fooles and children. But if authority come arm'd with lawes, the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes of <hi>State,</hi> it can ſtrike terrour to the ſtoureſt heart. <note n="b" place="margin">Iuſtinian. in proaem. inſtitut.</note> No marvell then that the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17176:15"/> Emperour thought Maieſtie but adorned with armes, and to be arm'd with <hi>Laws.</hi> The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> let any peece of this furniture bee laid aſide, malice will level its ayme at that open part. Whether it bee the helmet for the head, or the breaſt-plate and ſhield for the body po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique. Thoſe <hi>helmet-lawes</hi> which doe fence the head are of the greateſt moment. Seeing on the ſafety of that, depends the welfare of the whole <hi>State.</hi> Our glorious <hi>Head</hi> hath receiu'd in this kinde, from the prouidence of Anceſtors, armour of proofe againſt all annoyance. Now bloody Ieſuits, thoſe ſly meſſengers of Antichriſt, are alwaies furniſht with <hi>meſſengers of death:</hi> Thanks be to God, this body of ours hath eſcap't in the head; for God hath dealt with vs, as with <hi>Dauid;</hi> by his protection,<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 140. <hi>verſ.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>he hath couered our head</hi> though we haue, as it were, put off the hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met: I meane, lawes to this purpoſe haue layen in a long ſleepe and for good reaſons of <hi>State,</hi> haue not beene executed. Yet wee haue with <hi>Achilles,</hi> receiued wounds in the heele, which are ſtill freſh bleeding in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour people. They beginne to putrifie &amp; to draw contagion through the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. But the ſword is now vnſheath'd; you haue is againe in your owne hands; 'twere
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17176:15"/> pitty it ſhould euer be put vp, till it hath cut off our home-bred corruptions, and giuen all forraine factours their fatall blowes. An ill man once ſpake like a good Cittizen, Act. 19. <hi>The law is open.</hi> And how can I vſe a ſtronger motiue then to preſſe your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences with your free leaue? His <hi>Maieſty</hi> told you, he did for a while <note n="d" place="margin">His owne word in his firſt ſpeech in the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, <hi>1623</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>conniue,</hi> but now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The law is open.</hi> It is open, I hope, for the Iudges to execute, it is open for accuſers to implead. Then hauing againſt theſe maine enimies the laws full ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage <hi>what ſhall wee doe according to law?</hi> The body of our State hath other pernicious adverſaries that dayly afflict it with conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall wounds. The extenuating of murther by the fauorable name of man-ſlaughter, hath coſt our King many a ſubiect, and this land euen ſtreames of blood. Tis not for me to cenſure the law; yet thus much I knowe; that the <hi>Law of Moſes,</hi> and the law of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, will ſcarce admit ſome of our limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Doth a man come preſumptuouſly vpon his neighbour? God tells you by <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> he ſhall dye. <hi>Ex. 21.</hi> But except he aſſault him vpon long-ſtudied malice, and purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed revenge, with vs he ſhall not dye. We ſay he did it in his anger; and he ſlew a man, not
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17176:16"/> murthered him. But old <hi>Iacobs</hi> propheticke ſpirit well knewe the minde of God; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuffered not his own ſonnes ſo eaſily to eſcape. <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.6.7.</note> 
               <hi>O my ſoule,</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>come not thou into their ſecret; vnto their aſſembly, mine ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour bee not thou vnited,</hi> for in their anger they ſlew a man: he blames their anger only not their malice: yet marke what followes; Curſed be their anger for it was fierce, and their wrath for it was cruell, <hi>I will diuide them in Iacob, &amp; ſcatter them in Iſrael.</hi> Here anger and the heat of blood could not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe the ſpilling of blood. They felt the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor and full weight of Iuſtice: yea the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vieſt puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that then was, a <hi>Patriarchs</hi> propheticke curſe. And in conſcience ſuch reſolute hot-ſpurres deſerue with vs that <hi>Curſe of Moſes;</hi> the heauieſt temporal one that now is, <hi>Curſed is hee that hangeth on a tree, Deut. 21.</hi> Moreouer blood is importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate; each drop whereof hath a tongue, and cryes lowd at the throne of Heauen. Or if that were ſilent, your owne eyes are truſty witneſſes of many a widdowes teares. And the vntimely death of murtherd fathers bids their orphant children ſolicite your eares with their ſad lamentations. I, but the death of murtherers will doe them no good; admit
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17176:16"/> It doe not; yet let not their life doe others hurt. Let not the lawes indulgence encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage their bold hands to the like attempts: but ere others feele againe the extremitie of their violence, let them firſt feele the extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of your iuſtice; and to the vtmoſt that the law inioynes, let them knowe, <hi>What you can doe according to law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is alſo the ſwearer, whoſe tongue wounds the State, and like a ſharpe ſword ſtrikes deepe euen to the heart: hence it is that the land mourneth, ſaith the Prophet. No maruell that this ſinne is growne licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, for they ſay, 'twas lawleſſe and without the verge of iuſtice. Till at laſt that honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable aſſembly of Parliament (which poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſhal admire no leſſe for religion then for their wiſdome) haue reſtrained the freedome of this crying ſinne. It concern'd your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours to further ſuch a religious purpoſe; not only for aduancement of Gods glory, but to enlarge your owne liberty; for til the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a blaſphemous tongue might ſweare God and you in the face: you might tremble and bluſh you could not puniſh. Twere pitty this free crime (which <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> counts <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Tit. Hom. <hi>15.</hi> Ad pop. Antioch.</note> worſe then murther) ſhould longer violate the law of God, and Magiſtrates not be able
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:17176:17"/> to ſay, <hi>What ſhall we doe according to law?</hi> I could ſhew you other offenders, which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly among vs are lawleſſe; but with God they ſpeed like S. <hi>Paules</hi> Gentiles, which hauing not the Law, are a law vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. <hi>Rom. 2.14.</hi> But I muſt haſten to the ſecond ſenſe, <hi>No more then the Law in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends;</hi> of which exceeding briefly, <hi>What ſhall we doe according to law?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A depraued gloſſe may corrupt the Text; and a corrupt Iudge may depraue the Law. Thus truth that in the Oratours time had ſtrength enough for its owne defence, is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to yeeld vnto crafty violence. Chriſt alſo that originall truth found the perverſe Phariſee and petty-fogging Scribe wreſting the derivatiue truth to their own bent. <note n="g" place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Apion.</note> 
               <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephus</hi> may bragge of the <hi>Iews</hi> priuiledge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue other nations, in that they ſuffered no cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge in their laws; yet by his leaue though they remain'd intire in words, they were much peruerted in ſenſe. Thus could the wit of iniquity ouer-reach Gods intentions, and inhance its owne advantage by the miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of his precepts. I wiſh that while we looke vpon thoſe times in deteſtation, God hath not cauſe to looke vpon ours in revenge. I pray God <hi>the ſword of Iuſtice</hi> doe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:17176:17"/> neuer among vs become the <hi>Sword of Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phos,</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Eraſ. Adag Chil. <hi>2.</hi> cen. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that ſerued for all purpoſes:</hi> as thoſe groſſe flatterers abuſ'd it in the cauſe of <hi>Cambyſes,</hi> who deſiring to marry his owne ſiſter, was aduertiſd by them, that there was no law which allowed that copulation: but there was one, that he being their King might doe what pleas'd him. How doe ſuch Iudges befoole their Anceſtors! inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating that they doted and ſpake at ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, for enacting conſtitutions no ſurer then the old oracles, that might admit of a double ſenſe.</p>
            <p>Wel-deſeruing antiquity hath made this land of ours as happy as any; by leauing vs ſo ample an inheritance of laws and ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Twere ſhame not to preſerue them as inviolable, as thoſe of <hi>Solon</hi> and the<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.8.</note> 
               <hi>Medes,</hi> that ſufferd no repeale. Now to racke them beyond their literall intention, I count the higheſt degree of violation; Seeing extreme right is extreme wrong: and when a law is not executed at all, it argues but too much lenitie, negligence or ignorance; but being wreſted beyond its intent, and ouer-execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to a mans preiudice, it condemnes the Iudge of vnchriſtian-like malice. Then 'tis ſafeſt breaking the law in the Iews extream;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:17176:18"/> who hauing charge and power to giue <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.3</note> 
               <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſtripes</hi> to a malefactor, would (as <hi>Paule</hi> witneſt of them) <hi>giue but fortie lacking one.</hi> 2. Cor. 11. That they came ſhort, charity may hope 'twas commiſeratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his affliction: but ſhould they exceed the law, wee might ſuſpect their mindes for bloody revenge. Then let the law of <hi>Iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> be my laſt exhortation. <note n="l" place="margin">Iudex ne aliter indicet quàm legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus aut con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutionibus aut moribus proditum eſt. Inſtitut. lib. <hi>4.</hi> Tit. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Index ne aliter iudicet, &amp;c.</hi> And as <hi>Balaams</hi> feare engaged his fidelity co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the word of the Lord; ſo let Iuſtice deale with your conſciences concerning the word of the law. If <hi>Balaack</hi> would giue me his houſe full of Siluer and Gold, I will not goe beyond it to doe leſſe or more, <hi>Num. 22.18.</hi> In which reſolution the Lord make you proſper. So ſhall you be of their number that had their robes waſht in the Revelation: <hi>and made white</hi> in the blood of the Lamb. This awfull colour of State ſhall then turne to the pleaſing lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre of glory. And as you liue to glorifie God here, God grant you liue with him in his glory hereafter. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
